"Carbadox, the Carcinogenic Drug
Fed to U.S. Pigs but Banned in Other Countries"
In the late 1960s, carbadox,
a new feed additive
which promoted growth in chicks
was also found
to promote growth in pigs.
It is now fed to more than
40 percent of young pigs
in the United States,
not only to increase
rate of growth
but to control
diarrheal disease, too.
However, carbadox
is also a genotoxic
and mutagenic carcinogen
in animals.
More than 25 years ago,
the European Commission
banned the use of carbadox
in meat production
due to its possible
adverse effects
on human health.
Stating "it is not possible
to set a threshold
for a genotoxic
(DNA-damaging) additive
below which" there is no risk
to the consumer,
since even a small quantity
could provoke
a tumor-inducing mutation.
Other countries followed.
Canada halted its sale
more than 20 years ago,
and the Food
and Agriculture Organization
and World Health Organization
joint committee
on food additives
decided there is
no acceptable intake amount.
So, why is a drug
banned in many countries
still being fed to pigs
in the United States?
Well, one reason
is that the drug maker
has been defending carbadox,
sold under
the brand name Mecadox,
since the U.S.
Food and Drug Administration
first proposed
rescinding its use
based on concerns
about the persistence
of carcinogenic residues
in meat.
And no surprise
the National Pork Producers
oppose the FDA's proposal
to ban it,
likely because,
just as the drug company's
marketing brochure says:
"Bottom line, Mecadox can
help you market more pork"
and make them more money.
We're talking about more than
$20 million a year
with sales
continuing to increase.
The pork industry claims
that removing carbadox
would inevitably increase
use of other antibiotics
and the likelihood
of antimicrobial resistance.
If it really cared
about antibiotic resistance,
maybe pork producers would
stop feeding millions of pounds
of medically important
antibiotics to pigs
every year
in the United States.
And carbadox can actually
activate dormant viruses
that can transfer
antibiotic-resistant genes
among bacteria.
This can lead
to bacterial whack-a-mole,
where using carbadox
in pig production
may help prevent
some bacterial infections
but can also lead
to the emergence of bacteria
that are resistant
to antibiotics
used in human medicine.
There's a stalemate at the FDA
as the drug maker
keeps battling
to continue selling carbadox,
and the FDA keeps conceding
to its demands.
As of November 2023,
there seemed to be some hope
of the FDA withdrawing carbadox
from the market,
but we are still waiting
on final word.
In the meantime, carbadox,
with its 97.9 percent
likelihood
of causing cancer in humans,
is still banned
in many countries
around the world,
and it's still
being fed to pigs
bound for the supermarket
in the United States.